[Music]
yes hello good afternoon
from berlin to all of you tuning in for
yet another
discussion of the gdp live format
my name is jorg asmussen i'm the ceo of
the german insurance industry
association and i will guide you through
today's discussion where we will focus
on the solvency ii review
this is a topic maybe not at the
forefront of the political discussion
uh
but i'm very confident that we have a
lively exchange of use by people who
know the topic
by heart
i will
as a moderator restrain myself
from taking much of the stage
i would very much welcome and introduce
our speakers today
we have allegra from herve patrizi she
is among many other things the ceo of
aegon in the netherlands
and we have two well-known members of
the european parliament marcus farber
and arrow heinromo
and i'm very sure that
in the let's say brussels bubbles none
of them needs any kind of
of introduction
but given that in a virtual event you
have an audience that come from all over
europe
i will do it very briefly
and i will start with allegra we are
very pleased that you join
our panel debate to my knowledge but i'm
new here it's the first time that you
joined a gtv live former so thank you
very much
for agreeing to join us
you are currently the ceo of argonne in
the netherlands you are a board
member of
argonne in general
yourself in various positions on the
dutch association of insurers
you have started your career as many in
the sector at mckinsey
then you moved on to prudential and you
joined aegon at the end of 2015.
so thank you very much that you are here
then we have marcus faber
he is a member of the european
parliaments if i may say since 1994
i thought you were still in school
marcus but you are not so
we are very happy that you are here you
have taken many
jobs in the european parliament you are
among other things
the epp coordinator in the committee on
economic and monetary affairs the akron
committee
most importantly for our discussion
today you are the rapper tour when both
the solvency ii review which we will
discuss today
and the newly introduced proposal for an
insurance recovery and resolution
directive
um
so we came across quite a number of
times in in your political career so
very welcome you back in our sight
markers here
and last but not least it's arrow heiner
i hope i pronounce your last name
correct arrow you are a member of the
european parliament for the s d group
uh you are also a member of the akron
committee
and you are the shadow operator on the
solvency ii review
for the s d group
you have held many position in your
previous
career among others you were the speaker
of the finnish parliament
and when we met first you were the
finance minister for finland between
2005 and 2007.
uh you have chaired your party in
finland so very glad error that we have
here here
on this gdp live format and
the format of today's discussion we
already have um
quite a bit of fun at it before we went
on screen today
it's a kind of new format it's a kind of
shared panel because in this kind of
panel
my life is relatively easy because
the panelists
will ask their fellow panelists their
questions on their topics of interest
and we will have two question rounds
the first one is on the more
quantitative aspects of solvency ii and
the next one is a bit more general on
the more qualitative
aspects so totally the floor is to you
and we start with the
core of solvency ii
these are the proposed changes to the
so-called long-term guarantee measures
and
to kick-start the discussion
i think it's relatively easy to give the
word to the ep rapporteur uh marcus
farber for his first remarks and
questions marcus
the floor is totally yours
yeah thank you very much york and uh ero
and if i may say allegra makes it a
little bit easier i think in english
it's okay
first of all thank you very much for the
invitation although we live in really
crucial times when we look to the news
every evening
the other news we get from ukraine
on the other hand uh things like
solvency ii review go on and therefore i
appreciate the initiative of
the german insurance association
to organize this panel
i'm very happy that
new york give us all the work a
moderator should do
thank you very much for that
so i will not go in in a lot of details
as i've been told to put first questions
but only to give a general remark uh we
have started our
work in the committee and we had already
a first session on the
mr
proportions
together with the commission we will
have a short time a hearing in the acorn
committee
on this proposal and i have prepared at
the moment which will be published in a
few days a working document there right
a lot of questions which we have to
answer during the day and of course i'm
in close contact with the french
presidency and with
the incoming presidency from czech
republic in preparing the negotiations
with the council so we are already quite
active although my report has been
published but that is
under preparation and then of course the
hot timing of the debate will start i
have two short questions the first one
ladies first to allegra
um
the commission proposal has struck a
somewhat different balance between
ensuring financial stability
and freeing up investment capacity
then the aeopa
technical advice has done
are you happy with the commission
proposal and where do you think further
adjustments are needed and my first
questions to aero
would but we often talk about insurance
companies and we too did already as well
being long-term investors
that made help supporting the general
economic policies of the european union
such for example the green deal
they can only do so if we set the right
framework for insurance undertakings to
do so so how do you intend to help
freeing up
investment capacities of european
insurance undertakings and i hope i did
know very well my moderating role in
this
discussion
please
so first of all marco thank you it's
always a sign of trust when such a
distinguished german like you ask a
person to call them by first name so i'm
very honored by that thank you marcus
and of course you can call me allegra
to to your question um i think it's a
very good question it goes to the
balance between the financial stability
and the investment capacity of insurance
and at the end of the day you know if
you take a step back emits all the
discussion of technical details and
certainly they're not lacking there are
very many technical details let's not
lose sight that the core
societal objective for solvency to
review um is really is unlocking
insurers potential to invest long term
in the economy i think insurers are
incredibly well placed for that
so it's instead of shooting for a
balanced outcome let's maybe try to be a
bishop
um and let's be clear about this i think
we can be ambitious because we're not
running in my view a choice between
safety and ambition
so if you look at european policy
holders they are very well protected i
think that solvency ii framework that
we've established now about six years
ago is really a strong one and your
european insurers
are very well capitalized even during
the worst of the economic shock from
covet in 2020 and even if you count sort
of for long liabilities that some of
them do have
so this isn't a question of chasing
capital reduction for its own sake
it is actually
um
there are actual measurement flaws in
our view in the solvency ii framework
that should be fixed
and they would be to great benefit of
the wider economy particularly at the
moment where we all agree
maybe the european european economy will
be challenged give to given the events
that are happening on some of its
eastern fronts
and the risk margin and the volatility
adjustment for example are something we
could look at
uh
similarly that leads to maybe longer
term liabilities that are overstated
because they basically assume that we
should sell them within a year at any
given moment in time so yes yes i do
support europe's transition to a carbon
neutral economy and i think that
insurers have a natural role to play as
long-term investors for the kinds of
green projects that we all want and need
but let me be clear if i thought that
current capital levels were exactly
right then i would oppose any reduction
in capital requirements in the review
even for a good cause like green
transition
the fact is in fact that the capital
levels do need adjustments in a view and
i'm talking not just as ceo of vegan the
netherlands but also as representative
of the whole dutch industry the dutch
insurance industry
and so i would say it would be a wasted
opportunity not to take advantage of the
fact that we can fix things now and
promote investments in europe as a
result and maybe give
you know i ride a lot horses i love
riding horses and there is an expression
to give a leg up
and i do think that this is a moment to
give a leg up to the long-term
investment
opportunities of the european economies
at the moment where maybe because of
circumstances it will need it
errol any thoughts from your side
yes indeed may i first thank you as an
organizer of of this panel discussion
really timely
event and very important i suppose sport
for you but also for us
as as negotiators of this important file
and may i thank thanks al also marcus
for his excellent question
uh happy to be with you uh we are living
in
at the point where it's really important
that we have all the channels open
that we can hear the experiences and
opinions of the
of the industry
we know the
important role of insurance sector
in our economy
and in our economies and of course
what becomes to the basic ideas of the
commission proposal i totally share them
green deal is something which is i would
say before the ukraine crisis and
russian attack it was
the most common word used here in such
parliament in our discussions i would
say in every committee
so how to make this screen transition
possible is an
is a vitally important thing for for
our group and i would say for the whole
parliament and this has been so for for
several months and years already now
and then
of course uh we haven't noticed for
quite long time ago
that we cannot do
make this
transition possible without private
investments without private money
we know the restrictions concerning
public money
and and spending public public money the
only possible way out of is is make sure
that the
private investors are ready to to be
part of this transition
and what we have seen now during recent
two three weeks is that
obviously we must accept
higher
aims for our transition we have must do
the transition in a more rapid way than
be taught
some months ago
and this also means that we have to look
both answers and possibilities of the
public sector
of our member states but also the
possibilities to create a front
joint front
between
european union our member states and
then
the private investors
this will be a hard time for ourselves
we will have really also difficult years
ahead of us because
all the suffering coming from from
ukraine
is something which we will
feel in in our skin also and that's
something which we have to accept to
help ukrainians
and here is big role also for the
economy
and
getting away from the
russian fossils is number one tasks for
the whole european union now
so then coming to the commission
proposal as i said uh i'm a friend of
the basic proposal and the basic ideas
already before the uh before the russian
attack and
everything but it has changed in our
in our attitudes and way of thinking
but then um
to make this change possible
it's really important that at the same
time we take very seriously
the
need for prudency uh in in also in the
in in serious world
um to my understanding
solvency 2 is still in the first place
it's a prudential framework
and
that must be always respected and we
must be sure that whatever we are doing
we are doing it in on a solid base and
in in a solid way for
for
for the years to come
i'm really glad and this is sincerely so
marcus that i can take part of this
negotiation process and and these file
negotiations when we have so experienced
uh
um rapper as as marcos is and this i
suppose makes things a little bit easier
to to go further we know all the
background what has been decided earlier
we can perhaps also understand
better the weak points and then i
suppose every group can
can
be behind the idea of getting more
capital to the green transition
and i hope that everybody can understand
that also the prudency side will be
important in the future stability must
be protected and this mean
is that we have to be very careful when
we are making the changes we have to
really know what we are doing
what are the consequences of our
decisions
and to make them in such a way that both
the industry and also the customers and
then the states can be happy to the
proposals
i hope that in the process which we have
just started we can find those
ways which are more secure to the to the
chains
and which are
making the right balance because as you
ask there is really need for balance
between the new investment possibilities
and then between the
stability i will look very carefully
on the comments made by eopa it's an
important authority
for the whole sector and it's important
that their concerns are also listened
during the process
in every case i i hope that this will be
an open channel i hope that
all the
negotiators all the shadows will have
all the information from the ncr sector
because of course you are the real
experts but becomes to the
effects and
and the consequences of of the possible
new
decisions think that has set the scene
very nicely
um
now it would be up to you if you are in
the mood to ask some questions for your
your fellow panelists
i know that you
are
always taking a great weight to consumer
protection in the short term and in the
long term
so maybe you
since you started in your remarks with
the prudential you
you might take now
perspective if you like
yeah
happy happy to do it and
if we think the solvency
review aims it really seems that there
is need for evolution and not for
revolution as has been said
uh during the
the first discussions quite often
so these proposals they really tried to
address some structural shortcomings
and respond also to various challenges
for example very low interest rate and
this is something which we have to
look very closely because that's
one of the big changes in in our
economic environment
so the idea of boosting investments by
insurance companies
is is an acceptable important one as i
said
the commission outlines the capital
reliefs necessary to achieve these goals
uh at the same time
as you said how to ensure this is a
balanced package and that also consumers
and clients get a good deal
and this is not only in the long run but
also in the short term
uh i know that the insurance sector is
one of these
industrial sectors which is always
interested in the best of the customers
but we ought to make sure
that this is something where every
company is having the same kind of
attitude and that we also have a
structure which makes sure
that the interests of the
of the clients consumers are are
respected
so
by the the
panelists in your we that's the internal
market for insider sector
already really materialized and if not
what are the main obstacles to be
tackled and how do you want to address
these in the framework of this file so
how to make sure
that the interest of the
of the clients consumers is respected
it goes to me or to allegra
i i'm i'm i would love to hear your
viewpoints marcus
first
okay if you if you don't mind okay thank
you very much because i think consumer
protection is of course a key element as
well and as you have
put forward or raised in your question
already things have changed i remember
quite well when we negotiated solvency
too no one thought on a zero interest
rate period for a long time
yeah this time the crystal ball gave us
fully different informations and if we
start today
i think we do not know what's happening
in 30 years
what will be in the crystal ball
for that so i think
it's very important to put the point of
view of a policyholder and the
policyholder has of course some
interests and i think if we speak about
consumer protection we should take the
interests of the polity policyholder
into account so what are the main
interests of the consumers what do they
expect
from an effective insurance regulation
so in my opinion there are only two main
objectives i think that is something we
can try to
help and to figure out firstly
i think they want to have safe and
stable insurance companies that can
deliver on their promises when they are
called to do so yeah if i do insurance
it's always a business of promises yeah
and and these promises should be
safeguarded
[Music]
it's not me
secondly many consumers use certain
insurance products mostly life insurance
as an investment vehicle especially for
the retirement for the private
care taking of the retirement and that
is of course a very welcome development
which we should support as legislators
so if consumers tie up a lot of their
capital for very long time periods and
that is a life insurance we do need to
make sure that it's worth their ride
hence they do not need to be able to
earn a reasonable return that over the
long run at least beats inflation
then i think we did a proper job in the
insurance companies as well yeah it's
their business but we have to
organize it so in order to do that
i think insurance companies need to be
able to invest in attractive assets as
well otherwise they will not be able to
earn such a return and pass it on to the
client that is something which i always
have in mind what is the benefit of the
clients
and i think in this area there's really
some room for improvement by allowing
insurance companies for example to
invest more in equities or to invest
more in long-term projects as you
described in your first remark for
example the old energy sector i think so
if i take the german example
we don't have access to uh gas from
north of africa because through the
pyrenees there is no pipeline
but we need an investment in those
infrastructure which is a long term
investment and could be done
for example by by insurers only to give
you one idea but it's not me to invent
those products
but it's us to invent possibilities and
as i did the consumer protection on the
method on the financial markets as well
i think there's a great difference in
the financial markets we had this
problem of
lehman certificates which have been so
sold a few years before we had the
discussion on with it
after
especially the bankruptcy of iman
we don't have these kind of products in
the insurance sector so we should not
overrule as
of course we have some problems i will
not mention the member state but we have
in one member center problem and error
we had a discussion with
eopa on this issue
but
in the most of the products we don't
have these problems what we saw in the
financial sector so i think if we take
the view
of a insured people of the
insurance holder then i think we are on
the right track
so i guess it's my turn and look i i
share a lot of the
of the observations that uh marcus just
made let me take a completely different
point of view in order not to repeat
and maybe not surprisingly i'm going to
look at it from
you know gender and inclusion maybe
because i'm a woman and i've only ever
been a woman and
so in my view the best way to ensure
consumers are protected is to make sure
that they do have access to a variety of
products and different types of color
and that does include that does include
long-term guaranteed products which
frankly in some aspects of solvency too
are becoming or are at risk of becoming
prohibitively expensive
and so savers should be able to have
active to those
and to be able exactly as marcus said to
expect a decent return
right and so if you look at it
a system that imposes excessive prudency
by for example assuming that at any
moment in time you would sell those
assets that are fundamentally
looking at the long-term view but
assuming that you're going to sell them
you know at the moment's notice will
make it harder to attract new capital
will make it harder
to provide
that return that is required put things
to work on both sides and let me take a
very simple example maybe again because
i'm a you know single mother of three i
take everything to a very low simple
example
but if i look at cars right they do
contain safety features to protect
passengers to protect children to
protect everybody in the case of an
accident
but we have been very thoughtful about
which features we thought were necessary
and which features we accepted the risk
of
we could have done cars that could have
hit any tree
and basically not have any harm to the
people inside and that would be a car
with a 30 centimeter thick reinforced
steel
also called possibly a tank
and that would make the car absolutely
safe nothing would ever happen but it
would also mean
that in this day and age whenever you
would try to fill it up for gas you
would use your entire salary
and we collectively have agreed that
there was
sort of something in between that was
probably not a safe if i take my
car and i drive it into a tree probably
the tree is winning
at least at a certain speed but at the
same time i can you know take my
children on holidays every once in a
while so the point is i think we need to
find exactly that balance
between safety and acceptance of risk
such that overall in the longer term
society is better off
and potentially today when i look at
solvency ii and some of the development
of solvency ii and i think that is what
marcus was arguing
we may not be striking that balance as
well as we should and so that is where
we need to wear our father and mother's
head as at the same time as ceo and head
of investments head
and try to say
what is the reasonable outcome here so
that we can achieve
safety at a reasonable price so that we
don't taxed unduly uh consumers which de
facto are already going to be taxed by a
high level of inflation
thank you to
the second round of interventions which
focus on consumer protection uh
allegro i really like your example that
was
i will remember this and reuse it
it's now up to you to to ask questions
to your fellow panelists i know
that given your current job and your
integration into the the global aegon
framework you always have a
have an international
context to which you you refer so how do
you see the our solvency ii debate which
is
from the legislative point of view a
european debate how do you see this in
the global context and how would you
deal with your fellow panelists here
thank you thank you europe so indeed i
think as the introduction
uh slightly gave it away i have been
active in the uk i am active in the
netherlands but i'm of italian origin
and from a belgian mother so i think i'm
the closest thing to
sort of a european parliament we can
find around
and so first question for you marcus um
and possibly you would expect this but
how do you see the solvency to review in
an international context in terms of
level playing field in terms of also if
i look closer you know not necessarily
looking at the whole world but just even
to the uk where they're saying that
their review
is going to try to
you know make sure that it enhances the
competitiveness
are we falling behind or
do we have ambition to stay in the level
playing field how do you see that
yeah thank you very much for this
question which of course is something i
have in mind as well
but
to be very honest
we should avoid that we have a race to
the bottom and
on the other hand i think with solomon
c2 we have developed a kind of gold
standard
for
insurance
regulation
and we should promote this gold standard
globally and not fall behind and and
fall into the trap what uk is going to
do but uh honestly what i got as
information from the united kingdom is
really that they are willing to make
full use
of the flexibility that brexit have
given them
so we should take note of these
developments and see
if they have good
ideas
i'm not sure about that but maybe they
have ideas and commission had on the
other hand we should look to other
markets as well it's not only uk who has
adopted they have adopted hundred
percent as they joined us before
other have
taken some ideas into account some ideas
they have not taken into account and i
think we should take a look on that as
well why they didn't follow 100 of
solvency ii regulations and we should
use
the possibility which we have now
with this proposal from the european
commission not
to to put everything on the head but
to
extend solvency to
um to tweak
the
machine where it is necessary but as i
said not to turn it on its head and i
think
then we
really have this development which is
necessary so acknowledging that there is
a competition for european insurance
companies
of course means as well that we should
refrain from going overboard because
that could be the other way as well
um
with introducing too many new
obligations and requirements
while the rest of the world is doing
just the opposite and as you said in
your last answer on error's question to
find the balanced approach
uh
not only on on risk and securitization
but on the other hand here as well on
what is needed
according to the experience we have we
solve c2 but looking as well what other
markets are doing i think would be a
good approach that we find this balanced
way at the end of the day so i think the
commission proposal
looks quite
acceptable some others look quite
burdensome
while not granting additional benefit
and i think we have to identify those
areas
and
if we have done that then i think we
have a proper
solution whatever united kingdom does
i'm a continent boy as a german yeah the
uk calls us a continent i'm a continent
boy and i'm used to this thinking how
the continent things in difference
to the united kingdom so
there will be difference but at the end
we should have to take care on the
insured people in the european union of
course on the competitiveness of our
insurers as well
and we should look how globally
solvency ii standards have been
implemented
to adjust in a proper way
and using this possibility from the
commission proposal to do so
so if i understand well and taking on on
this idea of beauty is in the balance
hero
you know bringing it closer to home
maybe to the member state the the
continent as uh as markets called
supposedly how in your view how should
the review consider the level playing
field across member states as an outcome
or sort of how should the parliament
look at big differences in the impacts
in different markets from the proposed
changes
uh
thanks for your for your questions uh
from my side i i would like to say that
i i see this question as two dimensions
the first one is what you already
discussed and what
marcus expressed also
that we have to look that the european
companies have the same possibilities
at the international arena as
as the
foreign competitors have
and this is more and more important
question because we have already seen
during recent years that also usa is
more and more protecting its internal
markets
this is perhaps not a question so much
what becomes to the financial markets
but it's also there included
and we know that china has done it for
four years and from the beginning of the
years
in international trade
and this is a very hard discussion for
european union
that
and i can see i can fee i can feel the
change here in the atmosphere
that we have to be ready to
to be very careful when we are doing
international
trade dealings for example and then also
when we are making decisions concerning
our own legislation
that we will give the best possibilities
for our european companies to survive
and and to flourish
i'm a great friend of international
competition and international trade but
i can acknowledge that there are
problems
that
we have to look because the bird is not
totally fair
and this comes also to the
working conditions of the europe
european companies i so
to say it in a nutshell i have the
feeling that we have to look more
carefully
that our companies have the same rights
as our international competitors have
then concerning the
european markets
uh
i'm still afraid and i suppose you can
share the same feeling that we don't
have real european markets what becomes
to the for example the insurance sector
and
this is a great disadvantage and and
also disappointment the development
towards european markets has been much
lower than we taught during earlier
years
and at the same time
the real
value and important
value of the european union is to make
sure that both european companies and
both
european consumers would benefit from
the
from the advantages of competition and
we ought to make it
possible that
insurance products can be delivered
without any restrictions concerning
member state
borders
inside the union so i think this is the
great task
both
on the banking sector and then also the
on the insurance sector to make sure
that we will create
step by step these internal markets
they will be valuable for for the
companies to get
the
deeply needed capital and then for the
consumers to get new
and cheap products at their disposal
but this comes then then there comes the
question of also the
of of the safety of the markets and also
the
the need
to have a well-functioning
uh supervision of the markets and then
we are in the discussion what happened
in slovak and
the problems that if you are buying
[Music]
from
companies from mainly
working abroad
do you have real safeguards in
in your
products and is somebody looking at the
risks of of these companies which are
not
operating from your own country
and that's the reason that i think that
to create these internal markets we must
have a very strong supervisory structure
and it means also to have european
supervisors
in the case the national supervisors are
not doing their
their
duties in in a proper way or if there is
some information mismatching
[Music]
also the proposal of our
uh
our
solomon c2
review will be in in balance and
creating new possibilities both for
business and for consumers
yes thanks a lot arrow uh i think
you are now lively again your picture
was for a few seconds frozen but i think
we got your message and your questions
you you moved on
already to the second part
of our debate which focuses more on the
qualitative aspect of the review
you have focused on
[Music]
let's say an eternal topic of us
europeans that's the completion of the
internal market
this is clearly key and there's always a
room for improvement
uh i don't know ever if you want to put
questions to your fellow panelists or if
we
just
move on in the second part of the debate
um
that's up to you whatever you like
otherwise i
i will look at marcus because i
know from his previous statements on the
debate what he sometimes has online on
his
from my side i'm ready to go further
okay good thank you very much then for
for the focus on the on the internal
market
marcos you have been
publicly vocal on the solvency too
really
the key rapporteur
uh
you have focused on that among many
other things um
on the principle of proportionality
uh
overall in financial services but also
in the
in the insurance sector this is also key
to the interest of the german influence
industry associations because we have
450 members and some of course are
obviously pretty large and globally
active others are
more focused uh more specialized or more
regionally active
um so i'm very curious to hear your
questions or remarks
on the commission's proposals when it
comes to the principles of
professionality
yeah thank you very much but if i may
continue what uh what era has said which
i think is very important and i think we
should take a few minutes for that as
well
of course we have to think whether we
have achieved what was one of the ideas
of solvency too long time ago to prepare
a single market
and of course
we have some improvements but we have
not yet a fully integrated single market
for
insurance endurances
and that is something we have to
take into account on the other hand and
the issue was now mentioned by hero and
by me
the slovakian case if i may call it so
puts of course the question how we have
to improve the rights of eu
in comparison to national competent
authorities as for the moment
we stick somewhere in between where the
national competent authority is not
ready
to deliver what has to be delivered
according to european rules and that is
of course the question if we have a
single rule book and solvency 2 is a
kind of single rule book
and this single rule book does not apply
in this special case
of course we have to rethink how to
improve that that the singular rule
books
rulebook applies everywhere in the
european union whatever happens and that
is something i think
and i share
that we have to address that issue and
we have to find an answer on them i had
already contacts with my finance
ministry in germany that you know very
well york
from your time there but
and and i said to them very clearly not
every member state has a baffin
and even on the baffin we have sometimes
problems
as we learned with firecart so
we need a better structure between the
european oversight structure with the
europa and the national competent
authorities that is i think something we
have to to address but coming back to
your question which of course is of
course very important as well
i think what commission has proposed on
proportionality is a good starting point
i know as well it is not as easy as in
the banking sector as i was one
of the inventors together with peter
simon from the smd group in those times
for
this proportionality
approach on the banking side in the
crcrd
but
i think some of the ideas can be taken
into account
and
as you may remember and those who are
not dealing with banking sector it was
not only size it was as well risk model
because we said very clearly a small
bank with a high risk profile cannot be
dealt
similar as a small bank with a low risk
profile so risk is the other issue
but i think the proposal from the the
commission goes in the right direction
to address this issue of proportionality
and even before i was nominated
rapporteur
i had the honor to sit on some panels
on the preparation work commissioner has
done
and and i was always that's why you
brought it up i think
um discussing this issue as we really
have to think
that we have to address the european
problems and to give
national competent authorities
especially where we have low risk
profiles
and more possibilities not every problem
in europe has to be answered by europe
uh that's how we translate subsidiarity
and proportionality is of course
in to be seen in parallel to subsecurity
so therefore i think we will do further
improvements and i'm open for all
proposals coming from the various
political groups how we can improve this
proportionality approach
but um
[Music]
the the starting point given by the
commission helps a lot maybe we will
identify further issues
but
in any case if we keep the risk approach
in mind then i think we are on the right
track
yes
thanks a lot marcus if i may
comment yes the
proposed framework
regarding professionality is a big step
forward
and i think it's it's useful to
introduce the concept of low risk
entities as we also refer to it's not
just devices
business model
what i think is that the current
proposal
excludes especially in germany but
that's true to many other larger member
states
uh
sme insurers
because the absolute size criterium
which currently stands in the proposal
at 100
million euros gross britain premiums for
non-life
that keeps out
smes irrespective of their business
model or their risk profile so it might
work and i say this with all
you european respect and smaller member
states
but for the larger member states it does
not really fit because with 100 million
gross written premiums and non-life you
are you can be very small in in italy in
france or in germany
so we would suggest
maybe to introduce
valid nice criteria
so the aim could be
a share of 20
of the
the total market volume
that could be
a relatively sized criterion
and that takes better into account the
the heterogeneous
uh national markets
and of single companies inside
the common market
that's just an idea
for the discussion
i'm very happy to hear your idea but we
had the same discussion on the banking
sectors
and there was one proposal to make it uh
proportionate to the
gross national product but i don't know
whether that makes sense we will
discuss all these
in between us and then open for all
amendments and then we will see what's
on the table
but um if you have a single rule book
you should stick to a single rule and
not make it too complicated i understand
all these issues and in our mata is a
little bit smaller than italy and
luxembourg is a little bit smaller than
the netherlands but
we will find a
good proposal at the end of the day but
honestly
we had the same discussion on the
banking sector and we made a figure and
not 27 figures
it but twenty percent of the total share
is the same figure for every market get
it but i got your message marcus
uh
maybe we can move a bit on
allegra i'm i'm not sure if ergon has a
view on proportionality given
the size of your operations
uh
but feel free of course any time
uh given that that you operate or that
you as a person can't be others in the
netherlands if there's a view on
proportionality
there if not i i want to move on with
let's say a level playing field among
sectors whatever you want feel free
well look i can give a few a few remarks
on it so you're right if i take my head
as an aegon representative
proportionality is a bit of a less
important concept for
a pretty complex group like us you know
scrolling several continents so yeah i
can see that but if i take my hat as
representative of the netherlands which
is i would say by european standard a
mid small country then it is a very
important topic for the dutch and maybe
even for the smaller german markets and
across the european industry so
our view is that you do need
proportionality to ensure a diversified
insurance market which is better for
consumers if i were to take a crazy
examples if i forced each one of you to
wear high heels
i would be very comfortable i don't
think any of you will be that happy
right even if it's in the rules
so i think we need to make sure that you
know there is some choice in
intent but at the same time we do
support the concept of a rulebook we
support the automatic application of
proportionality this is not something
that a low risk undertaking should go to
the supervisor and back four this is
something that should come also from
that rulebook but at the same time
proportionality should be risk-based so
there should be no exclusion no
exclusions for non-risk-based criteria
for example the absolute size of an
insurer so i think look as as everything
in proportionality beauty will be in the
balance we need to find something that
makes sense but at the same time doesn't
get
an undue accumulation of risk with
certain players
got it i'm i'm tempted to comment on the
the high heels experience but
my my spokesperson which i knew i knew
it would raise a flag i knew it
yes i will not i will not do it because
i'm not insured against that and i will
need a statement i will have to visit
the hospital afterwards yeah but think
about it women are 50 of society and
somehow we have decided that the norm
are flat shoes think about that think
about that right proportionality where
does it stand where is it i always do i
always do but it's not my favorite
subject it will never become
arrow stays out of the high heel debate
i keep it stance
looking a bit at we have a little bit
less than 10 minutes left allegra do you
want to have a focus and questions or
remarks on the
level playing field between sector
when you look at confidence when you
look at bangs it goes a bit across
solvency too it has a bit to do
with recovery and resolution where where
marcos also is the rapporteur era is not
but maybe you like to flag visit it
yeah so i think that's a that's a very
good hint you're giving me and and
building up on the spies that i've
constructed until now let me stay on
something slightly more challenging and
have the same question to each one of
you which is
what are your views on applying banking
regulations to insurance are there
differences in the business models that
should be taken into account or is a
one-size-fits-all approach appropriate
let me just tell you for full disclosure
that we have a strong point of view on
that as insurers but i will let you
answer without leading the witness too
much
so it goes to me as robert thank you
very much i was not aware when i started
the first discussions with
the commission
on on zorran z2 that they are preparing
the ird in parallel and i was a little
bit surprised like other market
participants may have been surprised by
this proposal because as we discussed
now with proportionality where i
appreciate that things from the banking
sector are transferred to the insurance
sector
on the
ird i have some doubts whether it makes
sense to transfer it
as a banking rule to the insurance rule
and if you look to the commission
proposal and of course i took a lot of
inspiration from the banking world it
does not fit to the insurance world and
therefore we have to
improve what is the the insurance world
problem and we have to address if we
identify an insurance world problem
and
honestly and we had a first discussion
ero was joining
with the commission on that um
there have been a lot of remarks from my
side and from the colleagues
the shadow rapporteurs on the question
of
insurance guarantee scheme or something
like that the igs which is not a solid
c2 or ird issue it would be a special
legislation
but i had the feeling that was more in
the interest than
to have a one two one transposing
to the insurance sector like the ird is
so we have to see do we have
the same kind of systemic risks which i
don't see
and
being bankrupt and secondly
um as we have this question of
market coverage criterion
which i think is not a justified one
and therefore we have to really look in
the depth how to address this issue so
we should also take into account that
due to the nature of the business
for uh failing insurance undertaking
phase a lot more slowly than a failing
bank
yeah failing we had now this experience
with spare bank which was politically
intended but
fully supported it
we have to take care that in the banks
we have bank runs but i never saw
insurance run
yeah and what does it mean
um so on the banks we have to take other
protection mechanisms and then we did it
for for a good reason but i can't put
them one to one
to insurances because i've never seen an
insurance run
yeah
and so
sorry maybe i'm blind but i have never
seen it so um i think as we have more
time and more business continuity
uh so we should take more uh
or concentrate our work on recovery and
less on resolution and i think that is
the main difference
for insurance against banks where of
course resolution is an issue which has
to be addressed as well
so
we have not yet finalized the discussion
and i hear from the council a lot of
remarks which i think goes in the
direction alegre was not trying to
mention i know that there are member
states who are really not happy with the
whole proposal there are some member
states who are more happy but
no one is hundred percent happy so i see
a huge space for improvement there's
space for improvement especially as we
have to address the insurance world and
that is not the banking world
we would aggressively agree with you
but maybe we have to find some answers
which are not making you as happy as you
may be now
fine but at least
at least it's well suited
yeah
yeah as i said for example for me it's
more important what's happening with the
life insurance if my insurer goes
bankrupt
and
as i had some cases on my desk not every
member state has national systems in
place we have different quality of
systems in place
but that will be a legislation by its
own
but maybe we start a process now via
solvency and ird discussions
to um
ask commission for
for further improvement in that area for
only to give one idea but that is after
the first round of discussion which was
raised by a lot of colleagues all over
the politics so therefore i think that
could be one of these issues
which has to be addressed and will not
make all of you very happy i know but we
are legislators and that means we have
to keep everyone likely unhappy or
unlikely happy
let me
try to come to an end after a very rich
debate with
one procedural question
to marcus since he drives the procedure
as the key rapporteur
uh what is your time frame
or your intended time frame for for
dealing with the solvency with you
i tried to describe it in the beginning
jerk and i repeated of course no problem
the time frame is that we will now have
this hearing
we will have my working document as a
starting point to addressing the
questions to be answered
and then i will present my report after
the easter break then we will have the
time for preparing amendments and then
of course it will be
at the time then to negotiate in the
negotiation team without the shuttle
reporters i don't know how many
amendments i get i remember in the
midfield i got 2 400.
can you imagine it's a nightmare to find
compromises that will not be done in one
meeting so you have to identify the core
elements of interest from the colleagues
and then of course to find the
compromise
and then the
earliest vote would be after summer
break
and then start negotiations with uh with
the council under jake later's swedish
presidency but i hope we can start under
czech presidency
and as i heard from council they will be
ready maybe before summer break maybe
after summer break but in august we
normally do not negotiate so we are
quite parallel
okay thanks for this this very clear
timeframe i like to thank the three of
you for the lively debate on a very
technical issue i think you touch upon
many
key elements of the proposal is it
long-term guarantees is it consumer
protection
then we move to more broader
general topics like how you compare
insurance and banking
how do we deal with the internal market
when it comes to insurance
um
how do we deal with small and
medium-sized insurance companies so
thank you very much
uh that you have
joined us for this new format uh of a
shared panel of gdd live
i have enjoyed very much this format
because it makes my life very easy i
hope that that you do it as well so
thank you very much to the three of you
for joining us we will discuss
different formats again and again before
we come to a final closure
i also would like to thank our audience
who is watching us on linkedin twitter
or on our internet access gdp live
we
very much would like to welcome you soon
again
for the next gdp live event it will
already take place in april
we will at that time deal with the
timely topic of the european debate data
sharing open data
access the data
this is key for for insurance company as
well as for banks and
financial markets participants i would
thank as always because i can very much
rely on them to my team at gdp who has
set up this event here so
especially thanks to the three of you
enjoy the rest of the day stay safe stay
healthy
thank you very much
thank you sure
thank you thank you very much indeed
[Music]
foreign